all right so now we are in chapter six a
recipe for Designing active inference
models
Abraham Lincoln give me six hours to
chop down a tree and I will spend the
first four sharpening the ax
all right Ali what does the quote mean
and please lead us in to this discussion
okay so as the opening quotation
suggests it's about
uh honing these skill sets uh and skill
set for applying active inference
framework to model uh the actual
empirical uh
situations that we want to we may use
active inference for and it frames it as
a four-step recipe to
actually do the this kind of model uh
although it's turned as recipe but uh I
believe it's more like a guideline and
it's not like I don't know cooking
recipe that needs to be uh needs to be
observed
strictly so
it's more like suggestions or guidelines
to uh to begin to apply active inference
framework in any kind of situation
uh we'd like so uh section 6.2 outlines
those four steps
so the first step is which system are we
modeling
uh in terms of
how we can Define the market blankets
that most effectively and efficient the
problem or question and we want to
explore through that modeling through
the modeling of that situation so uh
first step is about defining those
boundaries of a
through marker blanket and the second
step is about what's the most
appropriate form for the generative
model because obviously we can have many
different types of uh generative models
depending on again what phenomena or
what questions we're trying to address
the third stage is
how to set up the generator model so
after
settling upon the type of degenerative
model we want to use
we can talk about the details of the
generator model and how it can be
efficiently modeled to be both tractable
and also
useful to address the situation of
interest and finally how to set up the
generative process so as we saw in
chapter two uh there's a
important uh that slight distinction
between generative process and
generative model so they're not always
the same but they're closely related to
each other generates a process to the
hidden states of the external world and
generative model is how the agent infer
about those hidden States
provided by generative process so uh
considering that the environment is
always very complex to be modeled
precisely and exactly with every
parameter accounted for we need to have
a restricted set of parameters to
account for in the generative process so
that's what stage four
deals for deals about so all of these
steps
even if not
uh observed or followed sequentially are
really
I mean essential to setting up I mean or
the initial setup of uh the situation
we're trying to model and uh
I cannot imagine how
any scenario can progress without
observing any of these
any of these steps at least uh I mean
just by thinking about how to set up the
situation or scenario
awesome and in the rest of the rest of
the chapter yes
just wanted to
um highlight again these steps don't
have to be followed in order they really
are like a summary as Mark has just
written in the live chat here it really
is like a summary of the earlier parts
of the book in terms of things that you
want to capture in your consideration
and also it's a great way to connect a
lot of the technical ideas that are
brought up about generative model
generative process and so on with some
bigger questions like who are we why are
we making this model how is the model
going to be used so we take that in a
lot of different ways in the textbook
groups but which system are we modeling
what is the most appropriate form for
the generative model
how should we set up the generative
model and how to set up the generative
process are all questions that must be
addressed at least when actually coming
through with carrying out a theoretical
or empirical octave inference modeling
task
and the following sections are going to
go into more detail on each of those
four questions so Ali do you want to go
for this 6'3 and carry on
okay so section
6613 is the elaboration of the first
step that we just saw
which I mean what systems are we
modeling and by this question
we mean how I mean what kind of system
uh
I mean how the system carves up the
state space using the markup blanket or
more precisely the active States and
sensory States and I believe it is
and both one of the most fundamental and
also one of the probably one of the most
challenging steps uh to be carried out
because
um
well markup blanket is just a conceptual
tool we use to frame uh the natural
phenomena or any other scenario we want
to model so that scenario or that model
obviously doesn't care about how we set
up our markup blanket or how we need our
markup blanket but uh
deciding on a proper a set of active
States and sensory states that would
allow us to address the problems we need
to explore or the questions we need to
answer
is not a trivial task and it needs lots
of lots of consideration and even
creativity on part of the
researcher or anyone who wants to design
an active inference based model for the
problem so that's where
the I mean the significance of doing
doing these kinds of modeling with the
insights and creativity of a
a researcher is I mean will be obvious
because it's not just something
mechanical or uh despite the fact that
the word recipe uh
can somehow make us believe that it's
just a recipe to follow but uh in
actuality it's not the case at all so
that's
uh
the discussion of Marco blanket and how
what
criteria we need to keep in mind to
settle upon the proper
uh yeah proper markup blanket around our
system and the next section
what is the most appropriate for form
for the generative model so here again
we can have various
way to set up our generative model in
terms of whether it's discrete or
continuous variables we want to account
for
about the time scale is it shallow or
hierarchical about uh or about the
temporal depth of the inference and
planning so these are all problems we
need to
be precise about or questions we need to
precise about and whenever we want to
set up our generative
model
and then we go to section 6.5
how to set a sorry yeah how to set up
the generator model so after the
precisely describing what needs to be
accounted or what parameters and the
nature of the generative model needs to
be accounted for
uh then we will probably need to address
this question of how can that generative
model be actually set up so
setting up the variables for the
generative model will
I mean we will be able to be concerned
about how those matrices as a b c and d
matrices matrices can be defined as we
saw in chapter four and then which parts
of the generator model are fixed and
what is learned so again it's really
important to know what are the Dynamics
of the of those parameters are in terms
of
the learning process and what what needs
to be updated consistently or learned as
opposed to the variables that uh either
don't require consistent updating or
they vary
quite slowly as compared to the time
scale of the generative model
and then we go
through the process of setting up the
generative process and as I mentioned
earlier it is probably one of the most
complicated uh steps of the recipe
because of the complexity the I mean the
enormous complexity of
any real-time situation
and particularly the environment that
the agent uh will act and behave but
even if not having uh I mean even if
there is not any um
strict or I don't know obvious way to go
through the through this stage of
setting up the generative process this
section provides some helpful
criteria or helpful points in order to
help us
um
in that stage as well so finally
after going through all of these stages
we need to somehow get I mean obviously
we need results and we need to
provide our results in a we get our
results from our active inference model
and uh
section 6.7 addresses that
uh I mean the the that very idea of how
to simulate visualize analyze and fit
data using active imprints because it's
not just enough to set up the model we
need to get the model to work so how can
we feed the data into the model how can
we
read the data and finally how can we
analyze or analyze the simulated data
through the
active inference so this is
uh in a way
um a kind of preliminary recipe or
preliminary procedure for doing active
inference or an active inference
modeling or at least suggested way uh to
uh to do those kinds of modeling but in
the subsequent chapters in particular
chapters seven and eight will go through
some uh helpful cases studies uh for how
to actually use these procedures
um to model some real world situations
awesome thanks well there's a lot to say
on chapter six
one piece that comes up a lot is what is
in the active inference kernel the
cognitive kernel and what are situations
that we can model with active inference
there's a huge variety of cognitive
phenomena and statistical outcomes that
we might be interested to study like
counterfactuals and planning like
multi-scale attention and covert action
like the complex ways in which memories
might
um influence decision making in the
moment based upon associations made
between different sensory modalities
every amazing real world situation you
can imagine
and it's really helpful to think about
active inference as more like a
framework of
interoperable motifs that we can compose
and indeed even be creative with rather
than giving us all the answers at the
core model because the kind of essential
minimal active inference model doesn't
necessarily include every single
attribute that you might be interested
in just like any given linear regression
isn't going to include every single
feature that you're looking for this is
happening in a different type of
modeling framework but still there's a
lot of customization and development
that goes into adapting or elaborating
an active inference type model for your
given system or scenario of Interest
chapter 6 gives us some helpful
guidelines and things to consider which
we've unpacked and expanded on elsewhere
and in the textbook group we work
together to characterize different
systems of interest to map different
parts or different observables from that
system using the active inference
ontology into a unified active inference
type model so chapter 6 starts the
second half of the book which is the
more practice oriented part of the book
and the rest of the part two is going to
be a lot more about the specific kinds
of generative models that you can use
discrete and continuous time and about
using them with empirical data in
chapter nine but chapter six just stands
alone as a summary of part one of the
book in some ways and a set of four
questions which system or remodeling
what is the most appropriate form for
the generative model how to set up the
generative model and how to set up the
generative process so that we can be
active inference model ourselves
all right well Ollie thanks so much for
all of these great uh conversations and
cohorts
we will be able to process this video to
clip out these first versions of the
background and context overviews and
we'll distribute them to the cohorts so
that people can show up with their
Curiosities and passions and we'll see
where that goes any last thoughts
thank you it was a pleasure to go
through these chapters once again with
each time obviously with uh a bit more
understanding than than the previous one
so I'm looking forward to the next
cohorts
awesome all right thanks Ali farewell